Hello again!
In this new section, communication between a reader and a cart.
So what's a smart card?
According to ISO 7816, a smart card, chip card, or integrated circuit card, IC is any pocket sized
card that has embedded integrated circuits.
This is a very open definition, which obviously would cover not only the objects you would spontaneously
name smart card, but also the SD card of your digital camera or mobile phone.
The cartridges of the gaming console you use to play with as a child, and possibly a flat USB flash
drive.
Actually, all of these are pocket sized cards that has embedded integrated circuits as well, but they
are no smart cards.
At first, let's circumscribe the subject to what the engineers and the industry have standardized under
the technical name Smart card.
An AC card having a standardized size, featuring a standardized electrical interface, implementing
a standardized protocol, and finally exposing standardized software interfaces.
All these standards are grouped in the ISO 7816 cluster entitled identification cards.
Integrated circuit cards.
So what about form factor and electrical interface?
ISO 7816 says the form factor of a smart card must be id1, as defined in ISO 7878 ten.
For example, the credit card size we all know is as the one that you are seeing here in this first
part.
A few smaller form factors have been introduced year after year by mobile phones manufacturers and are
now widely adopted.
For example, we have the two F mini SIM for the mobile phone manufacturer, which has also been adopted
by the smartcard industry for security Coprocessors.
Sam under the name ID 000.
Then we have three F, which is a micro SIM.
And then we have the four F, which is a nano SIM.
Which are that are used only in smartphones.
So the card communicates with the external world using a set of physical contacts, which also provides
power and clock.
I will not go deep into details concerning only the engineers working on the electrical interface,
but there are three facts worth noticing.
There are three power classes.
Class A stands for VCC equal five volts.
Class B, which stands for VCC, equals 3.3V.
And class C for VCC equal 1.8V.
A general purpose smart card reader is responsible for powering the card with increasing voltages until
the card comes to life.
A reader that is designed to always read the same card or the same card family could be optimized to
support only a single power class.
As you can see, contact S, C4, C6, and C8 were required in the 80s because the IC technology of
the time required a higher voltage when programming for like erase or write the memories than when reading
them.
These contacts have been deprecated in the 90s, but are now gaining new rules.
Some cars may implement USB on C4 and See8, and in some NFC enabled smartphones.
C6 is a direct link between the SIM card chip and the NFC contactless front end.
In early generation cards, CLK was the unique lock.
So when I say CLK, I mean clock was the unique clock source for the chip's processor.
Nowadays, most cards have an internal clock source, yet the clock line is still required to clock
the serial communication.
The reader must supply a constant clock signal, as you may know.
So what about the protocol of communication?
So ISO 7816 dash three specifies that the card implements as an asynchronous serial transport protocol
over the input or output pin.
The bit rate is defined as a division of the input clock.
The smart card protocol must put an emphasis on the error detection and recovery schemes in order to
improve the overall reliability of the link, because dirty or even damaged contacts are the cause of
frequent communication errors.
Actually, in fact, there are two protocols.
T equals zero is a character oriented protocol.
Error detection and recovery takes place after every byte.
Here we are talking about parity bit plus acknowledgement.
This is a legacy of the early 80s, a slow protocol yet usable even in harsh conditions.
Then we have the protocol T equal one, which is a block oriented protocol.
In fact, the blocks are 16 to 20 5 to 256 bytes long.
It's lots faster than t equals zero in the nominal situation where no communication error ever occurs.
But on the other hand, the error recovery process takes more time.
So since there is only one signal input or output pin shared by both input and output lines, both protocols
are half duplex.
The communication uses a command or response model.
The reader sends down a command, and the card must provide its response in a given time frame.
The only exception to this half duplex scheme is the initial power up and reset sequence, when the
card sends its first message spontaneously.
This message is the card's answer to reset or enter the ATR contains all the technical information the
reader needs to operate the card.
The protocol the card supports, the maximum bit rate and the expected timings.
For example, the ATR also conveys a few free bytes, like for example, max 15 bytes named historical
bytes that the developer of the software running in the car's microcontroller may use to expose some
information or metadata.
In a way, the ATR is a fingerprint of the card family.
The ATR allows a card aware application to determine whether a card that has just been inserted in the
reader is possibly the one card that the application was waiting for, or could be ignored.
So when we talk about communication between a reader or a card, I mean between a reader and a card
in contactless or contact technology, we will.
We talk about comments and answers.
So what about the comments?
In fact, the ISO 7816 dash four specifies that the comments Apdu starts with A44 byte header.
First byte is named class or CLA as, and it's intended to directly route the comment to one of the
cards applications or to control a secure communication channel.
Second byte is named instruction or INS, and identifies the command that has to be executed by the
cards application.
Third and fourth bytes are named parameters or p1 and p2.
They convert the parameter to the instruction.
It could be a combination of flags or a 16 bit number depending on the instruction.
So after the header comes the optional data field.
The length of the data is specified by the LC field.
LC field means the length of the command.
There are two kinds of epidius.
Short epidius are limited to 254.
Byte of data with width length on one byte extended up ideas go up to 64 kilo bit of data with length
on three bytes.
So the earlier I said 254 bytes, but I meant 254 kilo bit of data on one byte.
This is for the short use and the extended APD use go up to 64 kilo bit of that with length on three
bytes.
Then the CPU is terminated by an optional length.
It tells the card how many bytes the caller is waiting for.
Symmetrical symmetrical symmetrical length could be on 1 or 3 bytes.
Then we have the responses.
In fact, the response APD has no header and no length field.
It conveys an optional data field.
If this field is present, its length must be consistent with.
With length, it's terminated by a two byte status word status word one and status word two.
The status word tell tells whether the instruction has been correctly executed or not.
So, for example, when we have the perfect communication, when we have a when when the card would
like to say to the reader that I perfectly received the command, the status word will be 90 000 90
000 means we have no problem of communication.
For example, we have an another type of status word which can be six, eight, 82.
These two bytes means that there is a problem of communication that the cards is not able to understand
the command.